<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.6">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-07-26T22:19:23+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Finvestik</title><subtitle>The most important investment you can make is in yourself.</subtitle><author><name>Harsh</name></author><entry><title type="html">Investment Vehicles - 2</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/investment-vehicles-2.html/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Investment Vehicles - 2" /><published>2020-07-26T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-07-26T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/investment-vehicles-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/investment-vehicles-2.html/">&lt;!-- &lt;h4 style=&quot;color: #000080;&quot;&gt;
  What is Financial Independence ?
&lt;/h4&gt; --&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;blockquote&quot;&gt;
  “If you wish to get rich, save what you get &lt;br&gt;
    A fool can earn money; but it takes a wise man to save and dispose of it to his own 
   advantage” – Brigham Young
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 style=&quot;color: #000080;&quot;&gt;
  Financial Planning Pyramid
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;br&gt;

&lt;img
  src=&quot;/img/posts/Financial Pyramid.webp&quot;
  style=&quot;
    width: 100%;
    height: auto !important;
    max-width: 1000px;
    -ms-interpolation-mode: bicubic;
  &quot;
  alt=&quot;Financial Pyramid&quot;
/&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
Now, We will move to the remaining investment options available in the market. If you haven't checkout first post then you can checkout

&lt;a href=&quot;https://finvestik.in/investment-vehicles-1.html/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; style=&quot;color: red;&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 style=&quot;color: #000080;&quot;&gt;
  2. Post Office Schemes
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
  This is like a savings account with a bank, except that it is held with a post office. There are 
  various saving and FD schemes available to invest. You can get all the detail of schemes from 
  official &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.indiapost.gov.in/Financial/pages/content/post-office-saving-schemes.aspx&quot; style=&quot;color: red;&quot;&gt;Post Office Saving Schemes&lt;/a&gt; website.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
 &lt;b&gt; Now, You might ask a question why should we go for POS rather than bank schemes ?&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
  Just think what if banks go bankrupt ? What about your savings ? How much you get back are the entire value or some fixed value ? 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
  Aww..wait, Don't stand up and rush to the bank and withdraw all your savings. There is a provision for this type of crisis. In FY 2020-21 budget
  The Finance minister proposed an increase in insurance amount for depositors in case of bank failure, the RBI has announced an 
  increase in insurance cover to ₹5 lakh per depositor, from ₹ ₹1 lakh. 
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
 &lt;b&gt;Here are 2 things to know about this scheme:&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
  1) All types of bank deposits including savings, 
  fixed and recurring, are covered under the scheme. The ₹5 lakh limit covers both principal and interest amount.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
  2) It is to be noted that this deposit guarantee is involved only if the bank gets closed. 
  It cannot be released if the bank is a going concern.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
  Now, what if your aggregated about exceed 5 lakh in particular bank? You will lose your entire capital. To be risk free in these situations
  I recommend every individual to maintain 1 POS account for their family becasue POS completely secure in nature as it's 
  backed by the Government of India &amp; it's never to get closed.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
  I hope you will consider this saving options and try to maintain your capital in a place where your risk is less or zero.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 style=&quot;color: #000080;&quot;&gt;
  3. Bullion
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
Investment in Gold &amp; Silver is favorite for all Indian consumer but rather than buying gold as an investment option we generally see as security in nature.
 Mostly we buy gold in forms of jewelry and generally not even think about selling gold unless and until there is a financial crisis.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There is a risk of theft in physical form and also if you put it in a bank locker than charges of lockers need to be considered while investing in physical gold.
On the other side nowadays the government is promoting buying gold in digital form. Gold in digital form fetches same return as gold in physical form and
Gold in digital helps liquidity in the economy.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Currently, Government is running an scheme of &lt;b&gt; Sovereign Gold Bond (SGB) &lt;/b&gt; to encourage people to buy gold in digital format. SGB also fetches 
the additional annual retun of 2.5% on purchasing of gold bond. You can checkout all the details on NSE website  &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.nseindia.com/products-services/about-sgb&quot; style=&quot;color: red;&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 style=&quot;color: #000080;&quot;&gt;
  4. Real Estate 
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
  The Real Estate sector is one of the most internationally renowned sectors.
  In India, real estate is the second major sector/employer following agriculture. In the Covid pandemic situation Real Estate is the most underperformed 
  sector amongst others. Also, Real estate sector highly unliquidated, We can't sell or buy property in a day therefore by looking current economic 
  situation it's not advisable to invest in any real estate property.  
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h4 style=&quot;color: #000080;&quot;&gt;
  5. Bonds/Debentures 
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
  Bonds/Debentures are a kind of debt instrument where the issuer (Govt agencies &amp; Companies) of the bond has taken a fixed amount from a person/institute and paid the 
  intrest at pre-define rate &amp; principal at time of maturity. The bonds generally have some locking period typically in the range of 5-10 years.
  This lock in period is also known as the maturity period of the bonds/debentures.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
Investing in debt mutual fund consider as a safer option than equity market but there are mainly 2 risk associated with bonds/debentures.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
&lt;h5 style=&quot;color: red;&quot;&gt;
  Credit Risk
&lt;/h5&gt;
  Credit risk is a measure of a borrower’s ability to repay a loan and the interest charged on that loan. There might be a chance that companies failed
  to pay interest and principal amount to the bondholders. In that case, before issuing any debt instrument to the public there has to be a credit risk 
  rating for the bonds/debentures. A high rating means there are very few chances of default on payment or vice versa.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;h5 style=&quot;color: red;&quot;&gt;
    Interest Risk
  &lt;/h5&gt;
    A Interest risk is a risk associated with the interest rates changes of any economy. If intrest rates are lower then respectively value of olders
    bonds are goes higher because whichever new bonds will assign in future that interest rate is lower than the previous. If interest rates are higher in economy
    then older bonds value is decrease compared to the new bonds.
  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
  Mainly people will invest in debt instrument via debt Mutual Fund. There are many types of debt funds including 
  corporate bond, liquid bond, overnight bond , short duration bond, long term bond. You can checkout all the debt &amp; equity mutual funds avaialble from 
  &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://groww.in/mutual-funds?q=&amp;fundSize=&amp;categories=%7B%22Debt%22%3A%7B%22type%22%3A%22category%22%2C%22value%22%3A%22Debt%22%2C%22subCategories%22%3A%5B%5D%7D%7D&amp;sortBy=3&quot; style=&quot;color: red;&quot;&gt;Groww&lt;/a&gt; application/website.

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 style=&quot;color: #000080;&quot;&gt;
  5. Equity (Shares)
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
  An equity market or share market is a market where shares(very small part) are issued and traded, It is one of the most vital areas of a market economy because it gives companies access to capital and investors 
  a slice of ownership in a company with the potential to realize gains based on its future performance. A companies shares can be through exchanges and it can 
  be hold in a demate account. A person can open a demate account with any brokers associated with exchanges. I personally prefer to have an account
  with &lt;a href=&quot;https://zerodha.com/open-account?c=UR4102&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; style=&quot;color: red;&quot;&gt;Zerodha&lt;/a&gt; &amp; &lt;a href=&quot;https://upstox.com/open-demat-account/?utm_source=refernearn&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;landing_page=ReferAndEarn&amp;f=GOD4&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; style=&quot;color: red;&quot;&gt;Upstox&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Equity market will give you high returns if an investment made upon certain parameters while managing the risk.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
  Reliance got listed on stock exchange in 1977. 10,000 Rs invested in reliance at the time of IPO now it become more than 2,10,00,000. while on the other side
  10,000 Rs invested in Reliance power IPO in 2008 got vanished and just left with 4 Rs. So before investing in equity market an in depth study required or 
  a person can invest through mutual fund.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img
  src=&quot;/img/posts/Reliance.webp&quot;
  style=&quot;
    width: 100%;
    height: auto !important;
    max-width: 1000px;
    -ms-interpolation-mode: bicubic;
  &quot;
  alt=&quot;Reliance Since IPO&quot;
/&gt;

&lt;img
  src=&quot;/img/posts/Reliance power.png&quot;
  style=&quot;
    width: 100%;
    height: auto !important;
    max-width: 1000px;
    -ms-interpolation-mode: bicubic;
  &quot;
  alt=&quot;Reliance Power Since IPO&quot;
/&gt;

&lt;h4 style=&quot;color: #000080;&quot;&gt;
  5. Mutual Fund
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
  A mutual fund is a type of financial vehicle made up of a pool of money collected from many investors to invest in securities like stocks, bonds, money market instruments, and other assets. Mutual funds are operated by professional money managers, who allocate the fund's assets and attempt to produce capital gains or income for the fund's investors. 
  A mutual fund's portfolio is structured and maintained to match the investment objectives stated in its prospectus. There is a best curated 
  blog on mutual fund topic by Zerodha varsity you can checkout
  &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://zerodha.com/varsity/chapter/introduction-to-mutual-funds/&quot; style=&quot;color: red;&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;





&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
  Now, that we have learned the various investment instrument 
  In coming blogs, We will explore the area of Insurance, How it plays a major role in your financial Independence till then &quot;STAY SAFE&quot;.✌️😀
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6
  style=&quot;
    font-size: 20px;
    background: linear-gradient(
      330deg,
      #ff9933 20%,
      #ffffff 50%,
      #138808 55%,
      #ff9933 100%
    );
    -webkit-background-clip: text;
    -webkit-text-fill-color: transparent;
  &quot;
&gt;
  Jai Hind
  &lt;img
    src=&quot;/img/flag.png&quot;
    style=&quot;margin-left: right; margin-right: right;&quot;
    alt=&quot;Flag&quot;
  /&gt;
&lt;/h6&gt;</content><author><name>Harsh</name></author><summary type="html">“If you wish to get rich, save what you get A fool can earn money; but it takes a wise man to save and dispose of it to his own advantage” – Brigham Young</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Investment Vehicles - 1</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/investment-vehicles-1.html/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Investment Vehicles - 1" /><published>2020-06-02T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-06-02T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/investment-vehicles-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/investment-vehicles-1.html/">&lt;!-- &lt;h4 style=&quot;color: #000080;&quot;&gt;
  What is Financial Independence ?
&lt;/h4&gt; --&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;blockquote&quot;&gt;
  “When it comes to investing, we want our money to grow with the highest rates
  of return, and the lowest risk possible. While there are no shortcuts to
  getting rich, there are smart ways to go about it.” – Phil Town
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
  Past few blogs, We have seen inflation and compounding and now we are at
  stage to choose our investment options and start creating our wealth.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 style=&quot;color: #000080;&quot;&gt;
  How to Choose Right Investment Options?
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;img
  src=&quot;/img/posts/Risk-Return-Liquidity.webp&quot;
  style=&quot;
    width: 100%;
    height: auto !important;
    max-width: 1000px;
    -ms-interpolation-mode: bicubic;
  &quot;
  alt=&quot;Risk-Return-Liquidity&quot;
/&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
  In any investment option risk, return and liquidity will affect our investment. Risk and return are working simultaneously with each other.
  There is a basic rule in financial world
  &lt;b&gt;&quot;High Risk, High Potential Returns&quot;&lt;/b&gt;&quot;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
  In a bank FD we get a return around 7% where the risk is very less also the
  returns. While in stock market risk and potential returns are high however there is a chance that the principal amount will not intact while investing
  in the stock market.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
  Now look at Liquidity, In bank FD we can break our FD whenever we want, while in stock
  market we can get invested amount after 2 days of selling shares.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
  We need to diversify across all the segments to manage our risk, return and
  liquidity. So let's start and select our best suitable option to invest.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 style=&quot;color: #000080;&quot;&gt;
  Investment Vehicles...
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  - Bank Deposits &lt;br /&gt;
  - Post Office Schemes &lt;br /&gt;
  - Public Provident Fund &lt;br /&gt;
  - Bullion &lt;br /&gt;
  - Real Estate &lt;br /&gt;
  - Bonds/Debatures &lt;br /&gt;
  - Equity (Shares) &lt;br /&gt;
  - Mutual Fund
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 style=&quot;color: #000080;&quot;&gt;
  1. Bank Deposits
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
  - Fixed Deposit - Investing lumpsump amount at a time.&lt;br /&gt;
  - Recurring Deposit - Keep on Investing monthly with absolute dicipline.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
  The most basic type of investment people do is in banks with either in FD or RD.
  But do we know what suite us and which scheme fetch the better
  return for an investor? let's checkout with small calculation.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img
  src=&quot;/img/posts/Fixed deposit vs recurring deposit.webp&quot;
  style=&quot;
    width: 100%;
    height: auto !important;
    max-width: 1000px;
    -ms-interpolation-mode: bicubic;
  &quot;
  alt=&quot;Risk-Return-Liquidity&quot;
/&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
  You can download the excel file from
  &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/file/d/1ebWOjfoFfAH_S6V3xR0ffbc7Xr7kE9V2/view?usp=sharing&quot; style=&quot;color: red;&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Here, I took the FD
  investment amount invested at one time and the same amount invested through RD
  in a span of 12 months. We can clearly saw that FD fetches more returns than RD.
  In FD invested money fetch the return of 7% per annum while in RD only 1&lt;sup
    &gt;st&lt;/sup
  &gt;
  month invested amount fetch return of 7% while the last invested amount only
  fetches the return of 1 month. If possible, you should try to invest in FD rather than RD.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 style=&quot;color: #000080;&quot;&gt;
  Emergency Fund
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
  In my first blog I have asked you a question to ask yourself
  &lt;b
    &gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-style: italic;&quot;
      &gt;Do I have emergency fund that last 6 months ?&lt;/span
    &gt;&lt;/b
  &gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
  Now, If your answer is yes then it's awesome else no need to disappoint,
  We will create our own emergency fund.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
  Before start investing in any of the above mentioned instrument first, We should have
  emergency fund that lasts 6 months. But here you might have a question how much
  money do I need to keep in my emergency fund? 
  
  &lt;h6 style=&quot;color: red;&quot;&gt;
    Emergency Fund = Basic household expenses x 6
  &lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
  From your income try to keep some amount on a montly basis and start creating
  emergency fund and put that money into saving account don't think of any return in saving account, 
  don't use it unless and until you have a financial crisis. Keep
  on evaluating your expenses every year and based on that maintain your emergency
  fund.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
  Now, that we have learned the 1&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; investment instrument and emergency fund. 
  In coming blogs we will see all the remaining investment options up to that try to get some basic information for other instrument options and &quot;STAY SAFE&quot;.✌️😀
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6
  style=&quot;
    font-size: 20px;
    background: linear-gradient(
      330deg,
      #ff9933 20%,
      #ffffff 50%,
      #138808 55%,
      #ff9933 100%
    );
    -webkit-background-clip: text;
    -webkit-text-fill-color: transparent;
  &quot;
&gt;
  Jai Hind
  &lt;img
    src=&quot;/img/flag.png&quot;
    style=&quot;margin-left: right; margin-right: right;&quot;
    alt=&quot;Flag&quot;
  /&gt;
&lt;/h6&gt;</content><author><name>Harsh</name></author><summary type="html">“When it comes to investing, we want our money to grow with the highest rates of return, and the lowest risk possible. While there are no shortcuts to getting rich, there are smart ways to go about it.” – Phil Town</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Compound Interest</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/compound-interest.html/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Compound Interest" /><published>2020-05-08T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-05-08T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/compound-interest</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/compound-interest.html/">&lt;blockquote class=&quot;blockquote&quot;&gt;
  &quot;The strongest force in the universe is Compound Interest&quot; - Albert Einstein
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
  Now, We have decided our smart goals and start saving money to achieve
  financial independence, But without compounding nothing can be achievable in
  financial world. Compounding leads your money to works for you instead of you
  works for money, So let's checkout how compounding works.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
  Suppose you have invested 3,00,000 rupee in fixed deposit at intrest rate of
  8% what will be the value after 10 years ? We will calculate the return by
  comparing compound interest vs simple interest.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img
  src=&quot;/img/posts/Compound Interest vs Simple Interest.webp&quot;
  style=&quot;
    width: 100%;
    height: auto !important;
    max-width: 1000px;
    -ms-interpolation-mode: bicubic;
  &quot;
  alt=&quot;Compound Interest&quot;
/&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
  You can download the excel file from
  &lt;a
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/open?id=1w69FlBF4cab_cDwRGS4dt6bIbBCy9nrc&quot;
    style=&quot;color: red;&quot;
    &gt;here&lt;/a
  &gt;. As we can see from table as more time passes more chances we give our money
  to compounded.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
  Now, you might have a question can I stop parking my money into saving account
  and start investing in FD? That's not the case we should never park all our
  money into a single instrument. We will check the various investment option
  and risk associated with the upcoming chapters.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 style=&quot;color: #000080;&quot;&gt;
  Rule of 72
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
  If Someone should ask you at the 8% interest rate in how much time my money
  will be double? You might take some time to answer this question but this will
  be easily answerable with the rule of 72.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
  Divide the 72 by rate of interest (8%) to calculate in how much time your
  money will be double, Checkout the previous compounding table to identify
  calculation. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;span style=&quot;color: royalblue;&quot;&gt;72 / 8 = 9 Years&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
  With the help of this rule, we can identify the time horizon for money to
  duplicate itself in investing so we can plan our investment accordingly.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
  Now, that we have learned the basics of financial independence like How money
  works ? What should be our goals? How to save money? this all concepts are
  just like book theories. Now, We will deep dive into practical things like
  various investment options in the market, insurance Planning, tax saving
  options in coming blogs up to that keep reading some below mentioned books to
  understand the financial theories and &quot;STAY HOME STAY SAFE&quot;.✌️😀
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
  &lt;span style=&quot;color: #000080;&quot;
    &gt;Books for Financial Planning for Beginners: - &lt;br
  /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;a
  target=&quot;_blank&quot;
  href=&quot;https://www.amazon.in/gp/product/1612680194/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=3638&amp;creative=24630&amp;creativeASIN=1612680194&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=harshbhut-21&amp;linkId=43bfb717c0ad0523297782560914b29a&quot;
  &gt;- Rich Dad Poor Dad&lt;/a
&gt;&lt;img
  src=&quot;//ir-in.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=harshbhut-21&amp;l=am2&amp;o=31&amp;a=1612680194&quot;
  width=&quot;1&quot;
  height=&quot;1&quot;
  border=&quot;0&quot;
  alt=&quot;&quot;
  style=&quot;border: none !important; margin: 0px !important;&quot;
/&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a
  target=&quot;_blank&quot;
  href=&quot;https://www.amazon.in/gp/product/1595555277/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=3638&amp;creative=24630&amp;creativeASIN=1595555277&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=harshbhut-21&amp;linkId=0386f82e16317a91eb754d72aa256708&quot;
  &gt;- The Total Money Makeover: Classic Edition: A Proven Plan for Financial
  Fitness&lt;/a
&gt;&lt;img
  src=&quot;//ir-in.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=harshbhut-21&amp;l=am2&amp;o=31&amp;a=1595555277&quot;
  width=&quot;1&quot;
  height=&quot;1&quot;
  border=&quot;0&quot;
  alt=&quot;&quot;
  style=&quot;border: none !important; margin: 0px !important;&quot;
/&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a
  target=&quot;_blank&quot;
  href=&quot;https://www.amazon.in/gp/product/1939438632/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=3638&amp;creative=24630&amp;creativeASIN=1939438632&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=harshbhut-21&amp;linkId=fdb00ad8f3f6702222be899c50952a04&quot;
  &gt;- The Richest Man in Babylon&lt;/a
&gt;&lt;img
  src=&quot;//ir-in.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=harshbhut-21&amp;l=am2&amp;o=31&amp;a=1939438632&quot;
  width=&quot;1&quot;
  height=&quot;1&quot;
  border=&quot;0&quot;
  alt=&quot;&quot;
  style=&quot;border: none !important; margin: 0px !important;&quot;
/&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a
  target=&quot;_blank&quot;
  href=&quot;https://www.amazon.in/gp/product/0241019443/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=3638&amp;creative=24630&amp;creativeASIN=0241019443&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=harshbhut-21&amp;linkId=cb24da40b7f4e47667f97e1e7b6fb936&quot;
  &gt;- The One - Page Financial Plan&lt;/a
&gt;&lt;img
  src=&quot;//ir-in.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=harshbhut-21&amp;l=am2&amp;o=31&amp;a=0241019443&quot;
  width=&quot;1&quot;
  height=&quot;1&quot;
  border=&quot;0&quot;
  alt=&quot;&quot;
  style=&quot;border: none !important; margin: 0px !important;&quot;
/&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;h6
  style=&quot;
    font-size: 20px;
    background: linear-gradient(
      330deg,
      #ff9933 20%,
      #ffffff 50%,
      #138808 55%,
      #ff9933 100%
    );
    -webkit-background-clip: text;
    -webkit-text-fill-color: transparent;
  &quot;
&gt;
  Jai Hind
  &lt;img
    src=&quot;/img/flag.png&quot;
    style=&quot;margin-left: right; margin-right: right;&quot;
    alt=&quot;Flag&quot;
  /&gt;
&lt;/h6&gt;</content><author><name>Harsh</name></author><summary type="html">&quot;The strongest force in the universe is Compound Interest&quot; - Albert Einstein</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Smart Goals</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/smartgoals.html/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Smart Goals" /><published>2020-04-29T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-04-29T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/smart-goals</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/smartgoals.html/">&lt;!-- &lt;h4 style=&quot;color: #000080;&quot;&gt;
  What is Financial Independence ?
&lt;/h4&gt; --&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;blockquote&quot;&gt;
  &quot;A goal without a plan is just a wish&quot; - Antoine de Saint-Exupéry
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
  I hope you have done your analysis on your spending habits and started saving
  money by cutting down your undesired wants and spending habits.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
  Now, We have some amount of cash in our hands to start investing in various
  available options in the market. Some of you might already be started investing in
  mutual funds but before started investing in any instrument, think for a second
  and ask yourself a question &lt;b&gt;Do I have any specific goal to Invest?  &lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
  If your answer is &lt;b style=&quot;color: red;&quot;&gt;No&lt;/b&gt;, Then it sounds like
  &lt;span style=&quot;font-style: italic; color: #808080;&quot;&gt;
    &quot;you are sitting in a taxi and asking a driver to just move
    wherever he wants to go and when he asks for a destination, you just tell him
    keep going I will tell you where I want to go afterward.
  &lt;/span&gt;
  this should not belong to us, right? We should have a destination to go in journey as well as in investment. We must have a specific goal and a plan to fulfill it, So
  let's check out how to set our smart goals in investing.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img
  src=&quot;/img/posts/smartgoal-types.webp&quot;
  style=&quot;
    width: 100%;
    height: auto !important;
    max-width: 1000px;
    -ms-interpolation-mode: bicubic;
  &quot;
  alt=&quot;Smart Goals&quot;
/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Let's understand it in terms of investing by an example. The actual scenario might
  different and it's based on the individual.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;b&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #de4645;&quot;&gt;Specific&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt; - I want to buy a car.
  &lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;span style=&quot;font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;
    - Here, I want to buy something and that is a car, so it's a specific
    goal.&lt;/span
  &gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;b&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #f9a824;&quot;&gt;Measurable&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt; - I need to save 10
  Lacs to buy a car. &lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;span style=&quot;font-style: italic;&quot;
    &gt;- Here, I require specific amount that will need in future to buy a
    car which is measurable.&lt;/span
  &gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;b&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #01897b;&quot;&gt;Time Based&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt; - I want to buy a car
  in 2 years. &lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;span style=&quot;font-style: italic;&quot;
    &gt;- Here, I defined my time frame that is 2 years. Within that time I have to save 10 lacs to fulfill my requirements.
  &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;b
    &gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #ffc928;&quot;&gt;Attainable &lt;/span&gt; &amp;
    &lt;span style=&quot;color: #7db343;&quot;&gt; Realistic &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b
  &gt;&lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;span style=&quot;font-style: italic;&quot;
    &gt;- These 2 go in line with each other if I said that I want to buy a ferrari
    in 2 years, It's neither attainable nor realistic in near future.&lt;/span
  &gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
  We need to set smart goals that can be achievable and realistic otherwise
  sometimes it will lead to disappointment by not achieving it. So before starting set smart goals and based on that decide which investment option
  is suitable for you.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justtify;&quot;&gt;
  Now, we know &lt;b&gt;What is smart goals&lt;/b&gt;, and &lt;b&gt;How to set smart goals? &lt;/b&gt; But do
  we actually know how to achieve them? So let's checkout
  &lt;b style=&quot;color: #000080;&quot;&gt;How to achieve smart goals ? 🎯 &lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justtify;&quot;&gt;
  To achieve goals arrange them in order of their time to reach. Usually, goals
  can be divided into 3 parts.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;span style=&quot;color: #cd00ea;&quot;&gt;Short Term - (0-2 yrs) &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span style=&quot;color: #ba00e5;&quot;&gt;Medium Term - (2-7 yrs) &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span style=&quot;color: #a200e0;&quot;&gt;Long Term - (7 yrs and more) &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
  Now, again these categories depend on individuals some of you might have just
  started working, some have just married, some might have at the age of thier
  retirment. So as per your requirement, categories your goals based on time and
  start investing accordingly.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
  We will now see various investment options available. But wait, every good story
  has a villain!!! Then think who is the villain in our story that stop us to achieve our
  goals ?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;span style=&quot;color: red; font-size: 35px;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;b&gt;😈 INFLATION 😈&lt;/b&gt;
    &lt;blockquote class=&quot;blockquote&quot;&gt;
      &quot;Inflation is taxation without legislation.&quot; - Milton Friedman
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;blockquote&quot;&gt;
  &quot;Inflation is a quantitative measure of the rate at which the average price
  level of a basket of selected goods and services in an economy increases over
  some period of time.&quot; - Wikipedia
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;/img/posts/inflation-rate-india.webp&quot; style=&quot; width: 100%; height: auto
!important; max-width: 1000px; -ms-interpolation-mode: bicubic; &quot; alt=&quot;Inflation
rate in India from 1984 to 2024 (compared to the previous year)&quot;&quot; /&gt;

&lt;h6&gt;sources:- &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statista.com&quot;&gt;Statista&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;h4 style=&quot;color: #000080;&quot;&gt;
  How inflation effect our investment ?
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;
   Today, you bought some goods for 100 rupees at the inflation rate of 4%, a year later to buy the same quantity of goods you need to pay 104 or you can say
   that value of money decreased by 4 rupees. &lt;br/&gt;

   Suppose you have parked 1,00,000 Rs in fixed deposit at the interest rate of 7%.
&lt;pre&gt;
  Initial Investment    - 1,00,000
  Interest Rate         - 7%
  1 yr Return           - 1,07,000
  Inflation Rate        - 4%
  Net Return            - 1,03,000
&lt;/pre&gt;
After a year net return is 1,03,000 which is only 3% of your investment. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:justify;&quot;&gt;
  You might have question how can we beat or reduce the effect of inflation
on our investment? for that you need to be familier with 8&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; wonder of world and that we will have some interesting talk in next blog upto that &quot;STAY HOME STAY SAFE&quot;.✌️😀
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h6
  style=&quot;
    font-size: 20px;
    background: linear-gradient(
      330deg,
      #ff9933 20%,
      #ffffff 50%,
      #138808 55%,
      #ff9933 100%
    );
    -webkit-background-clip: text;
    -webkit-text-fill-color: transparent;
  &quot;
&gt;
  Jai Hind
  &lt;img
    src=&quot;/img/flag.png&quot;
    style=&quot;margin-left: right; margin-right: right;&quot;
    alt=&quot;Flag&quot;
  /&gt;
&lt;/h6&gt;</content><author><name>Harsh</name></author><summary type="html">&quot;A goal without a plan is just a wish&quot; - Antoine de Saint-Exupéry</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Habits</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/habits.html/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Habits" /><published>2020-04-19T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-04-19T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/habits</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/habits.html/">&lt;!-- &lt;h4 style=&quot;color: #000080;&quot;&gt;
  What is Financial Independence ?
&lt;/h4&gt; --&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;blockquote&quot;&gt;
  &quot;It's not your salary that makes you rich, it's your spending habits&quot; -
  Charles Jaffe
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: left;&quot;&gt;
  I think before moving towards the first step of financial independence, it's
  better to understand the most basic concept of the financial world.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img
  src=&quot;/img/posts/Savings vs Investment.webp&quot;
  style=&quot;display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;&quot;
  alt=&quot;Saving vs Investment&quot;
/&gt;

&lt;!-- &lt;p style=&quot;font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;
 
&lt;/p&gt; --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Now, We can say that we should maintain a balance between these 
  2 in life to become financially independent but without having most 
  powerful instrument it isn't possible, Can you guess what?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;span style=&quot;color: red; font-size: 35px;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;b&gt;💰 MONEY 💰&lt;/b&gt;
    &lt;blockquote class=&quot;blockquote&quot;&gt;
      &quot;It takes money to make more money&quot;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt; 
  It's your &lt;b&gt; Spending Habits &amp; Money Management &lt;/b&gt; will decide wheather you will be successful
  in financial independence or not. Let's checkout average spending by common men
  from their income.&lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;
  Total Monthly Income                :  40000
  Essential Items                     : -10000
  EMI(Car, Home, Credit,Insurance)    : -20000
  Luxury                              : -3000
  Savings                             : -5000
  Other items                         : -2000
                                      --------- 
                                          &lt;b&gt;0&lt;/b&gt;   
  &lt;/pre&gt;
The main intension to show this calculation is that people are so much engaged in the daily work that they don't know about their spending habits. Money comes and goes in no matter of time from their pocket, Think about yourself and find out in which category you are? 🤔 &lt;br&gt;
Analyze your spending habits by looking at your past 1-2 month expenses and savings trying to make an excel from that workout you will understand the 
inflow and outflow of your money from your pocket.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Now, you might think that our income amount is the root of all our problems. Having a very small amount of income how can 
  we save or invest after all my expenses? you are right, Income is not directly in our hand but what is definitely in our hand
  is &lt;b&gt;expenses&lt;/b&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now, you might ask how to cut down expenses to save? I assume that you have done your analysis for your past few month's savings and expenses. So currently the calculation is to be &lt;span style=&quot;color: red;&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Savings = Income - Expenditure&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt; 
but ideally it should be &lt;span style=&quot;color: #0609d4;&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Expenditure = Income - Savings&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;. If you follow this habit then in a short time
you will have good amount of savings. Now, again you might have a question that how much I should save from my income? So Let's Checkout.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img
  srcset=&quot;
    /img/posts/fifty-thirty-twenty-rule-390w.webp 390w,
    /img/posts/fifty-thirty-twenty-rule.webp     800w
  &quot;
  sizes=&quot;(max-width: 550px) 390px,
            800px&quot;
  src=&quot;/img/posts/fifty-thirty-twenty-rule.webp&quot;
  alt=&quot;50-30-20 Rule&quot;
/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now, You already have a list of your spending habits for the past 1-2 months try to categorize items in above mentioned rule. Try to cut down 5% from needs &amp; wants categories and add that part of the money into your savings category. 
Try as much as you can cut down your expenses, better you reduce earlier sooner you will achieve your &lt;span style=&quot;color: #0609d4;&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Financial Independence&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  I know this is not very easy to suddenly change your lifestyle but believe me you can develop this &lt;b&gt;habit&lt;/b&gt; overtime by practice and 
  patience. In the next blog, I will explain smart goals and our enemy in investment.✌️😀
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6
  style=&quot;
    font-size: 20px;
    background: linear-gradient(
      330deg,
      #ff9933 20%,
      #ffffff 50%,
      #138808 55%,
      #ff9933 100%
    );
    -webkit-background-clip: text;
    -webkit-text-fill-color: transparent;
  &quot;
&gt;
  Jai Hind
  &lt;img
    src=&quot;/img/flag.png&quot;
    style=&quot;margin-left: right; margin-right: right;&quot;
    alt=&quot;Flag&quot;
  /&gt;
&lt;/h6&gt;</content><author><name>Harsh</name></author><summary type="html">&quot;It's not your salary that makes you rich, it's your spending habits&quot; - Charles Jaffe</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Financial Independence</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/financial-independence.html/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Financial Independence" /><published>2020-04-12T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-04-12T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/financial-independence</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/financial-independence.html/">&lt;h4 style=&quot;color: #000080;&quot;&gt;
  What is Financial Independence ?
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;blockquote&quot;&gt;
  Financial independence is the status of having enough income to pay one's
  living expenses for the rest of one's life without having to be employed or
  dependent on others.Income earned without having to work a job is commonly
  referred to as passive income. - Wikipedia
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: left;&quot;&gt;
  Now, You might think that why am I reading this ? Let me close the page and do
  my work but wait hold on for a minute. Just ask these questions to yourself.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;
  - Do I have any passive income ? &lt;br /&gt;
  - Do I have emergency fund that last 6 months ? &lt;br /&gt;
  - Do I have plan my life after retirment ? &lt;br /&gt;- Do I have any financial
  stability that pays my debt if I lost my job or business ?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  If you don't have answers then you should consider to change your spending and
  saving habit so it will help you to save from falling into financial trap.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;
  &lt;span&gt;Check out the surveys done on savings habits of indians.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;!-- &lt;img
  src=&quot;/img/emergency-saving-pattern.webp&quot;
  alt=&quot;Emergency Saving Pattern&quot;
/&gt; --&gt;

&lt;img
  srcset=&quot;
    /img/posts/emergency-saving-pattern-390w.webp 390w,
    /img/posts/emergency-saving-pattern.webp      800w
  &quot;
  sizes=&quot;(max-width: 600px) 390px,
            800px&quot;
  src=&quot;/img/posts/emergency-saving-pattern.webp&quot;
  alt=&quot;Emergency Saving Pattern&quot;
/&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;img
  srcset=&quot;
    /img/posts/monthly-income-save-390w.webp 390w,
    /img/posts/monthly-income-save.webp      800w
  &quot;
  sizes=&quot;(max-width: 600px) 390px,
            800px&quot;
  src=&quot;/img/posts/monthly-income-save.webp&quot;
  alt=&quot;Monthly Income Saving&quot;
/&gt;

&lt;!-- &lt;img src=&quot;/img/monthly-income-save.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Monthly Income Saving&quot; /&gt; --&gt;
&lt;h6&gt;sources:- &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dealsunny.com/blog&quot;&gt;DealSunny&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  You might think that all these things looks good on paper but how can I
  achieve that? Not to worry friends, We will together achieve
  &lt;b&gt;Financial Independence&lt;/b&gt;. So keep calm and Let's begin our journey ✌️😀
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6
  style=&quot;
    font-size: 20px;
    background: linear-gradient(
      330deg,
      #ff9933 20%,
      #ffffff 50%,
      #138808 55%,
      #ff9933 100%
    );
    -webkit-background-clip: text;
    -webkit-text-fill-color: transparent;
  &quot;
&gt;
  Jai Hind &lt;img src=&quot;/img/flag.png&quot; alt=&quot;Flag&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/h6&gt;</content><author><name>Harsh</name></author><summary type="html">What is Financial Independence ? Financial independence is the status of having enough income to pay one's living expenses for the rest of one's life without having to be employed or dependent on others.Income earned without having to work a job is commonly referred to as passive income. - Wikipedia</summary></entry></feed>